GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

Summary

Over 5+ years of experience in business analysis with a focus on business process management, process improvement, business systems analysis/development and implementation of full-lifecycle in IT, energy sector and banking services industry domains. *Demonstrated skills in critically conducting Requirement analysis, Data analysis, GAP analysis, System analysis, impact Analysis and Resource Analysis throughout the projects in evaluating/analyzing the existing standards and policies to determine the improvements. *Experience in Change Management, application development and maintenance, application enhancement and production support area *Full Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) experience including Analysis, Design and Review of Business and Software Requirement Specifications, Development, Testing and Agile software development methodology. *Hands-on working knowledge of Business Process Re-Engineering (BPR), Business Process Management/Modeling (BPM) Process Mapping, LEAN principles for Process Improvement. *Application of PMBOK, BABOK guidelines, experience with Agile and waterfall methodologies, iterative practices and Six Sigma Green Belt. Skills

Engineering Management, Business Process Improvement, ARIS, DMAIC, Six Sigma, Project Management, SAP ERP, Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC), Software Testing Life Cycle (STLC), Minitab, Microsoft Office, Business Process Mapping, Business Process Management, Process Analysis, Process Design, Process Transformation, Process Organization, Process Performance Management, Enterprise Process Management, DMAIC, FMEA, SIPOC, Project Documentation, Minitab, Six Sigma, SharePoint, Core Java, Java Server Pages (JSP), JavaScript, Eclipse, Business Development, Integration, SQL, Test Planning, Consulting, Requirements Analysis, Requirement Load, Requirement Planning, Requirement Communication, Requirement Elicitation and Requirements Management, Business Analysis, User Acceptance Testing (UAT), Requirements Gathering, Customer Relationship Management (CRM), Enterprise resource planning (ERP) system deployment, SAP Business Objects

Accomplishments

- Six Sigma Reduction of defects in crayon manufacturing assembly line.
- Implemented the DMAIC knowledge to reduce the defects in the crayon manufacturing assembly line.
- Defined the CTQ (Critical-to-Quality), SIPOC, operationally defined each CTQ, performed Gage R&R (Repeatability and Reproducibility).
- Analyzed data using Minitab 17.
- Used the I-MR charts, T-test and performed the root cause analysis, identified the potential failures for the Process Failure Mode and Effect
 Analysis, determined which process step has the highest RPN and improved the process of crayon manufacturing.

Experience

08/2016 to 05/2017

Graduate Teaching Assistant

- Tutored and supervised a class of 35 students.
- Managed, critiqued class discussions, grading assignments and quizzes and maintained my office hours while excelling in the courses I had enrolled.
- Communicated and responded to students' queries and prepared the teaching material for management classes.
- Helped in the additional exploration of given topics and to clarify the doubts of each and every student about the materials.

06/2012 to 07/2015

Business Process Analyst, Team Leader, Tech Mahindra Metropolitan State University Of Denver il/4 Denver

- Conducted interviews and brainstorming sessions with key business users, process owners, and subject matter experts to understand the
 process flow, listed any undocumented information in SAP system.
- Recorded and captured the discovered processes and recognized areas of improvements.
- Used best practices for processes.
- Worked with different functional department managements like Refining and Manufacturing, Operations Management, Financial Controls
 and Accounting, Security, Human Resource Management and Information Technology to review and recommend changes.
- Acted as a single point of contact and helped in updating the current processes (around 1173 processes in IT track), workflows, procedures and in improving efficiency and throughput.
- Applied Six Sigma and Lean methodologies to process improvement initiatives.
- Identified projects from project selection, process elements, benchmarking, SIPOC analysis, and identified owners and stakeholders.
- Performed requirements analysis: requirement load, requirement planning, requirement communication, requirement elicitation and requirements management.
- Identified and documented business requirement documents (BRD), use cases, functional specifications, and entity relationship diagrams (ERD), RACI charts, activity diagrams and process flow diagrams using UML modeling tools such as MS Visio.
- Facilitated JAD workshop with multiple stakeholders for understanding the overall process/content structure, visioning of to-be state, business needs and discuss improvement opportunities.
- Developed change management plan to continually monitor individual progress to ensure meeting of milestones.
- Applied Quality Assurance practices to identify any risks and document issues.
- Assessed the flaws in the existing as-is system and made clear recommendations of business process improvements (BPI) and reduced the duplicated business processes by 50%.
- Performed gap analysis for modules by having discussions with SMEs.
- Understood, documented the impact of process changes and communicated different alternatives and measured changes with appropriate metrics.

- Documented business processes and analyzed procedures to see that they would meet changing business needs and developed to-be process flow diagrams and documents with the help of as-is process flow using graphical business process modeling tool- ARIS.
- Communicated the capability of business needs and used the business process modeling and analysis (BPMA) tools, methods and standards
 like the Business Process Modeling Notation (BPMN).
- Lead the conversion effort of creating over 1500 business process workflows for Reliance Industries Limited existing business process repository.
- Managed a team of 20 offshore ARIS modelers to create and deliver around 600 process workflows and supporting documentation.
- Used various stakeholder inputs to justify, establish project boundary and performed the cost-benefit analysis.

04/2011 to 05/2012

Business Process Analyst, Tech Mahindra Reliance Industries Limited i1/4 City

- Collaborated with senior business analyst and project manager on project charter, current-state analysis, and requirement and specification documents.
- Conducted requirement gathering sessions.
- Reviewed and updated requirements through change management and drafted process maps.
- Documented requirements, conversations, meetings, decisions and sign-offs.
- Designed and implemented user set- up, end user training materials and testing procedures.
- Conducted user acceptance testing (UAT) of the developed applications along with the end-users and arranged training sessions for contractual employees on business process.

07/2010 to 03/2011

Java Developer, Tech Mahindra BASF i1/4 City

- Responsible for coding and integration of systems, test plan preparation, user documentation, development and peer review of unit test plans and code reviews.
- Implemented SMS engine application which is an automated component for sending bulk messages.
- Prepared and arranged for software components release.
- Performed system administration for hosting server and client software.
- Developed JSPs and Servlets.
- Developed screens using Java, HTML, DHTML, CSS, JSP and JavaScript.
- Identified various software issues using debugging process and coding techniques.

Education and Training

May 2017

Master's: Engineering/Industrial Management University of Houston - Clear Lake Engineering/Industrial Management 3.9/4.0

Bachelor of Technology : Electronics Engineering Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University Electronics Engineering 3.8/4.0 Skills

Accounting, benchmarking, Business Analysis, business analyst, Business Development, Business Objects, Business Process, business processes, Business Process Improvement, change management, charts, clarify, Consulting, content, conversion, Customer Relationship Management, CRM, CSS, client, debugging, Documentation, DHTML, Eclipse, Engineering Management, ERP, Enterprise resource planning, Financial Controls, functional, HTML, Human Resource Management, Information Technology, Java, JSP, Java Server Pages (JSP), JavaScript, materials, meetings, Microsoft Office, Office, SharePoint, Minitab, Modeling, Enterprise, Operations Management, peer review, Performance Management, Process Design, Process Analysis, processes, process improvement, Process Management, coding, progress, Project Management, Quality Assurance, Requirements Analysis, Requirements Gathering, SAP, SDLC, Servlets, Six Sigma, SMS, Software Development, Software Testing, specification, SQL, system administration, teaching, user training, user documentation, UML, Visio